1972年，最后一次阿波罗登月任务圆满成功
The year is 1972, the final Apollo mission to the moon has just been completed.
总统尼克松发表了关于新飞船的重要讲话
And President Nixon has announced a new American Spacecraft.
“这是人类发射的最大的、带有机翼的飞船！”
"This is the largest spacecraft ever launched by man, the first winged spaceship”
“世界第一款可以重复使用的飞船”
“The world’s first reusable spacecraft”
那就是航天飞机
The Space Shuttle.
可以把多名宇航员和大型卫星送到地球轨道
Capable of carrying several astronauts as well as large satellites into Earth’s orbit.
设计航天飞机的初衷是想大大降低进入太空的成本
This new idea for a reusable spacecraft was meant to drastically reduce the cost of getting into orbit
而到后来，尽管航天飞机成功完成了上百次任务
and although the Space Shuttle did complete hundreds of successful missions,
但当年的承诺可完全没兑现
it never really lived up to everything it promised to be.
而现在，太空叉也要降低去太空的成本
Today, we have SpaceX making another attempt to cut the cost of getting into space.
那他们做法有何不同呢？
But what are they doing differently?
BFR会不会步航天飞机之后尘呢？
How do we know the BFR won’t become another Space Shuttle?
本期视频我们将对比BFR和航天飞机
In this video, we’re going to compare the BFR to the Space Shuttle
我们还将探寻航天飞机的失败原因
We are also going to look at what caused the Shuttle to fail
以及太空叉做了哪些改变让BFR不会犯相同的错误
and what SpaceX are doing to avoid the BFR having a similar fate.
最早的时候，航天飞机设计初衷是可重复利用与维护成本低
From the very beginning, the Space Shuttle was designed to be reusable and cheap to operate.
在航天飞机研发过程中，NASA估计航天飞机寿命是14年
During the development of the Shuttle, NASA estimated that the entire cost for the 14 year life span of the Shuttle
其间总花销450亿美元，平均每次发射5400万美元
would be around $45 Billion with the cost for each flight being $54 Million.
可NASA当时还是NAIVE！
NASA’s original estimates fell very short.
很大一部分原因是每次飞行后高昂的翻新费用
This was largely due to the incredible amount of refurbishment needed after each flight.
原本打算让航天飞机像民航客机那样每次飞行之间只是做做简单检查
The original idea was to have the Shuttle quickly checked out between each flight, just like an airliner.
这个过程原本以为只需大概两周，实际却要大约三个月
This turnaround process was expected to take around 2 weeks, however it would usually take around 3 months
几个月后……
痛快的啊！麻溜的啊！
Get on with it × 2
三台RS-25发动机需要全部拆卸下来翻新
Each of the three RS-25 engines had to be detached and refurbished after each flight
加之RCS的燃料是剧毒的
and since the propellants used for the RCS thrusters were so toxic
翻新RCS的时候其他工人只能干等着
no other activities could be carried out on the Shuttle while they were being handled.
而最浪费时间的翻新项目之一就是防热瓦
One of the most time consuming aspects of the Shuttles refurbishment was the heat shield,
整整三万五千块，每次飞行之前每块都必须单独安装
with each of the 35,000 tiles having to be inspected individually between each flight.
视频里用的是plan
但这里SpaceX后的谓语plan应该用单数第三人称形式plans
PICA-X: Phenolic Impregnated Carbon Ablator，酚碳热烧蚀板
太空叉打算用的隔热材料叫PICA-X
SpaceX plan(s) to use a material called PICA-X for their heat shield.
该材料设计为每次飞行消耗很少
Although this material is designed to wear away slowly after each flight
于是太空叉打算把它用上百次直到用坏换掉
SpaceX are aiming to get hundreds of uses out of it before it needs to be completely replaced.
如果太空叉想让BFR廉价且可复用
If SpaceX want the BFR to succeed in being cheap and reusable
那他们必须彻底掌握火箭复用的秘诀
they will need to master the art of rocket reusability.
“全回收”指两侧助推与芯级回收，不包括二级部分
目前重型猎鹰全回收版运力和航天飞机相近
The Falcon Heavy in fully reusable mode is currently capable of carrying a similar payload capacity to the Shuttle
但成本却是航天飞机的约五分之一
but for a fraction of the cost.
但即使他们彻底掌握火箭回收技术，他们也绝不能在安全方面让步
But even if they do master rocket reusability, they will need to do so without compromising on safety.
实际上，航天飞机最大的问题和它本身都没啥关系
One of the biggest problems in the Space Shuttle program actually had nothing to do with the vehicle at all.
主要还是来自NASA对安全的态度
It was in fact NASA’s attitude towards safety
在80年代（早期）NASA还是很宽容的
which started to become more lenient in the 1980's.
因为当时发射日程很满
Due to an incredibly ambitious launch schedule
NASA的高层决定搞大跃进！
NASA’s upper-level management started to embrace what many called “go-fever”.
NASA为了满足这些如此之浪的发射日程，忽视了很多安全条例
In order to meet these ambitious launch dates, possible safety hazards were ignored,
导致之后两起航天飞机的致命事故
which lead to the Space Shuttle experiencing two fatal disasters.
鬼才信
而BFR目标是2022年飞往火星
With the BFR aiming to make its first flight to Mars in 2022
对于太空叉来说最重要的就是避免为了赶死线而在安全上走捷径
it’s extremely important that SpaceX don’t follow a similar path of cutting corners in order to make their own deadlines.
这些年太空叉的另一特长就是在火箭设计上的快速更新能力
One thing that SpaceX have shown over the years, is their ability to make quick changes to the design of their rockets.
太空叉的AL曾说“没有一发猎鹰九号是完全一样的”
Andy Lambert of SpaceX once stated that no Falcon 9 was ever the same
工厂里的每一发新火箭都有与之前相比的升级
with upgrades being made to every new rocket that rolled out of the factory.
如此快速的更新让他们不断完善猎鹰九号的一级回收技术
This rapid development allowed them to perfect the Falcon 9’s propulsive landing technique.
然而这样的后果是各自会出故障的地方也会共享
However, they have also had their fair share of failures,
这是在BFR上万万使不得的
which won’t be an option once they start launching humans on the BFR.
另一个让航天飞机落得如此地步的原因是它的设计与制造过程
Another thing that held the Space Shuttle back was the design and manufacturing process.
其生产压力分散给了全美国很多承包商
The workload was spread across many different companies all over the country
从而制定更能让国会掏钱的计划
in order for the program to appear more attractive to Congress.
这不但提高了项目成本
This not only raised the cost of the program
还提高了航天飞机的制造复杂度
but also added an extra layer of complexity to the entire construction of the Shuttle.
而在那之上，更有NASA爸爸给航天飞机加上条条框框
On top of that, NASA had certain stipulations for the Space Shuttle,
总是要求使用一些过时的硬件而不是研发更新更有效的解决方案
often requiring outdated hardware to be used instead of developing a newer and more effective solution.
而太空叉的风格显然不是这样
Since SpaceX won’t need to adhere to such specific requirements,
他们能从一张白纸开始造BFR，而且每个零件几乎都是自己造
they can design the BFR from a blank canvas, and with nearly everything being designed and manufactured by SpaceX themselves
使得飞船的每个部分按照需求能完美配合
every part of the vehicle will work together, perfectly as intended.
所以尽管BFR吹得看上去有多不靠谱，总感觉要和航天飞机一样凉凉
So although a lot of the hype surrounding the BFR does seem reminiscent to the conception of the Space Shuttle
但太空叉真的在做出实打实的改变
it does seem like SpaceX are already starting off on a better foot.
而且按照他们之前成功的例子来看，我相信BFR将是非常一颗赛艇的！
And if their success so far is anything to go by, we know the BFR will be very exciting.
所以你觉得BFR怎么样？
What do you think of the BFR?
它能功成名就还是依然深陷节约成本的泥沼无法自拔？
Will it live up to its goals or will it struggle to achieve the low cost and rapid reusability that it promises to have.
欢迎在评论区讨论
Let me know in the comments below.
如果喜欢本视频，欢迎去下方链接资瓷YouTuber
If you enjoyed this video and would like to contribute to Primal Space, please visit Patreon.com/PrimalSpace,
达到50人会抽送土星五号乐高模型哦~
where we will be doing a giveaway of a Saturn V Lego Set once we reach 50 Patrons.
最后记得点赞投币收藏关注转发充电哦~让太空姿势深入寻常百姓家！
So make sure you’re subscribed so you can join the discussion as we continue to learn more about all things space.
感谢观看，字幕翻译给虫，我们下期见
Thank you very much for watching and I’ll see you in the next video.